大家好 我是凯超
Hello everyone, I am Kaichao
本次课程内容是Rust项目的代码管理
Today's course is about project management in Rust
课程内容包含
the content includes
Rust里常用的模块组件
commonly used modular components in Rust such as package, crate, module
如package, crate, module的介绍
如何引入功能模块
how to import such modlar components
最后我们会看一下workspace的简单使用方法
Finally we'll look at the usage of workspace
首先我们来看一下
First let's see
为什么要对我们的
why do we need do project management for our code?
代码项目进行管理呢
当我们的Rust项目变得很大时
When the project gets really big, there will be a lot of code
会有大量的程序代码
那我们就需要将程序代码
we need to splite code in different modules, different files
放在不同的模块下
不同的文件里
we need to splite code in different modules, different files
从而让代码更容易维护
so that the code become much easier to maintain
这跟我们的电脑桌面的管理是一样的
This is simlar to manage the desktop of our computer
当你有一两个文件的时候
when you only have one or two files on your desktop, that's fine
放在桌面是Ok的
但是当你有了几十
but when you have dozens even hundreds of files on your desktop
上百个的文件的时候
如果你不再分组管理那就不行了
it won't work if you don't move files into different folders
代码的模块化还可以用来封装无需外部关心的实现细节
Modular code can also be used to encapsulate the implementation details for its users
让代码实现复用
make the code reusable
当我们有了一段功能代码
When we have a piece of code which implements a function
别的代码需要使用这个功能
and other code wants to use this function
那只需要通过
it just need to call the public interface exposed from the implementation
该模块的公共接口
调用相应的功能就可以了
it just need to call the public interface exposed from the implementation
不需要在自己的代码里再次实现
there's no need to implement the logic again in its own code
也不用关心内部的实现细节
and the user don't need to care much about implementation details
Rust提供的代码管理组件包括
The components for code management provided by Rust include
下面几个
The first one is package
第一个是package
它是cargo工具用来
cargo command use this space to build, compile and test the code
构建编译测试的一个空间
也是我们工作的一个主要目录
it's the main directory for our work
那package里面呢
What about inside the package?
又分为很多crate
a package is divided into many crates
有我们本地自己写的crate 还有我们依赖的一些公共库
There are local crates written by us and some public libraries we depend on
我们自己写的如果是工具库的话
If it is a library, entry point is in the src/lib.rs
它的
入口文件在src/lib.rs文件里
If it is a library, entry point is in the src/lib.rs
那如果我们自己写的是一个可执行程序
If it's a executable binary, the entry point is in src/main.rs
那它的入口文件在src/main.rs里面
常用的一些公共的依赖库
Here are some commonly used libraries
包括rand来获取随机数
rand library is used to get a random number
serde对我们的json文件进行解析
serde to parse the json content
以及diesel对我们的数据库进行操作
And diesel to query and modify our database
那每个crate呢
How to manage a crate?
又可以进一步通过module进行划分, 组织代码
it can be further divided into modules for better code organization
控制不同module之间是否可见
By controling the visibility between different modules, we get clear interface
当某个模块需要依赖其他模块的时候
When one module needs to depend on another module
就需要引入对应的模块功能
you just need to import it by specifing the path of the module
那引入的时候我们需要指定路径
这里我们来看一个简单的模块树
Let's look at the folder structure of a simple package
根模块或者说是根目录
By convention, the root module or the root directory is usually called crate
是crate 它是一个约定俗成的名字
当我们内部定义了其他模块的时候
here we aslo defined a submodule inside it
比如这里我们定义了一个子模块
here we also defined a submodule inside it
在crate下面定义了一个子模块是front_of_house
it's named front_of_house
那front_of_house里面呢
What's in the front_of_house module?
我们又定义了两个子模块 分别是hosting和serving
it defines two submodules, hosting and serving
在hosting里面我们定义了两个函数, 是add_to_wait_list以及seat_at_table
In hosting module, we list two functions, add_to_wait_list and seat_at_table
以及serving里面的几个函数
and several other functions in serving module
当某个模块需要依赖其他模块的时候
If a module needs to depend on other modules
就需要进行功能引入, 使用的是use关键字
we can import the dependent features with the keyword "use"
在当前模块里面使用 pub use 某个功能的时候
With "pub use" keyword, we can not only import the feature, but also re-export it from current module
那这个功能会重新导出当前模块
也就是当前模块的依赖方
That is
也可以使用我们 pub use 出来的这样的一个功能
the modules that depend on the current module can also use the features from a 3rd-party module by re-exporting with "pub use"
crate我们刚才看到了它是一个
"crate" is represented as the root module of a package
根目录，根模块
self是当前模块的一个表示
"self" is represented as the current module
super是当前模块的父模块
"super" is the parent module of the current module
那我们还可以使用as关键字对我们引入的功能模块进行别名
We can also use the keyword "as" to alias the imported features
或者函数进行别名
现在我们来看一个简单的例子
Now let's look at a demo
我们首先创建一个新项目
We first create a new project via cargo new command, project
通过cargo new command, project
我们的项目名称是project-demo
The project name is project-demo
那我们来现在看一看
then let's see what's inside the project-demo directory
project-demo的包含的文件
它有一个Cargo.toml
There is a Cargo.toml, it's the project configuration file
是我们的项目配置文件
指定了我们项目的依赖以及项目的一些元信息
it specifies the dependencies and some meta information about the project
src文件是我们的源代码文件
the source code lives in src directory
那刚开始的时候它只有一个main.rs
it has only one file named main.rs when creating a fresh new project
我们进入到我们对应的项目文件目录
Let's enter into the project directory
然后打开我们的VScode
then open the VScode
可以看到它的一些元信息
we can see there are some meta information like project name, version, author, and the dependent version of Rust in Cargo.toml
比如我们项目名称, 它的版本, 作者以及依赖的Rust编译器的版本
那我们源文件里面的main.rs
The source code in main.rs only print "Hello, world!" to the console
它只有简单的逻辑就是打印"Hello, world!"
我们执行看一下结果
Let's run the program and see the result
可以看到我们这里已经打印出来了
You can see that the result is printed
Next
接着我们把我们的模块定义拷贝进来
let's copy our defined modules here
这里我们
which are the modules we just saw
就是我们刚才看到的那个模块树
我们有一个子模块是front_of_house
We have a submodule which is front_of_house
它里面有两个子模块一个是hosting, 一个是serving
there are two submodules in it, one is hosting, one is serving
里面各自定义了几个函数, 函数的功能都比较简单
There are several simple functions in it
就是简单的打印输出
just print some content to the console
现在我们来编译运行一下
Now let's compile and run
可以看到并没有额外的一些输出
You can see that there is no additional output
那我们在我们的main函数里面使用
In the main function, we can use the functions from hosting module
我们对应的模块功能
这里我们调用的是front_of_house hosting模块下面的add_to_waitlist的例子
here we are calling the function add_to_waitlist from front_of_house::hosting module
这样一个函数
我们编译执行
Let's compile and run
可以看到我们有一些编译错误
You can see that there are some compilation errors
原因是因为我们的
The reason is because the submodule is private
子模块是一个private的
我们需要通过关键字pub
We need to use the keyword pub to make the module public for others
来将我们的模块
对外可见
We need to use the keyword pub to make the module public for others
以及我们调用的函数也需要增加
we also need to make the called function to be public
可见性
其中front_of_house不需要增加pub是因为
the front_of_house does not need be "pub"
main函数和front_of_house这样的模块位于
because the main function and front_of_house are in the same module
同一个模块里
两者是彼此可见的
both are visible to each other, there is no need to add pub here
所以在这里不需要加Pub
接着我们来执行
Next let's run the code
可以看到我们现在已经成功的打印了add_to_waitlist函数的输出结果
You can see that the output from the function add_to_waitlist is successfully printed
那接着我们来重构一下我们代码
Then let's refactor our code
因为我们的模块
because our module
通常是要放在一个单独文件里
usually  needs to be in a separate file
而不是放在某一个main文件
instead of putting it in a main file
或者说其他文件里
or in any other files
我们把这个内容拷贝出来
Let's copy this content
增加一个新的文件
add a new file
叫front_of_house.rs
called front_of_house.rs
把对应内容粘贴
paste the corresponding code
当我们把对应的模块
When we put the corresponding module
代码移到一个分开的文件的时候
when code is moved to a separate file
我们就不再
we will no longer
需要最外层的这样的一个模块名
need a module name of the outermost level
相应的我们要在
Correspondingly we need to import modules in our main.rs
main里面引入我们对应的模块
接着我们来执行一下
Then let's execute
也是成功的
It is also successful
我们刚才提到过了
We just mentioned that
除了使用这种相对路径来指定我们的
instead of using this relative path to specify our dependency
所依赖的功能之外
我们还可以通过一个绝对路径
we can also use an absolute path
那他的根模块或者说根目录是叫crate
Its root module or root directory is called crate
我们刚才已经看到了
we have just seen
我们根模块下面的front_of_house
front_of_house under our root module
这样的一个模块
such a module
以及它的子模块hosting
with its submodule hosting
调用对应的add_to_waitlist函数
and add_to_waitlist function
那我们接着再次重构一下
Then let's refactor again
除了把我们的模块代码移到一个文件
In addition to moving our module code to a file
里面之外
我们还可以把它移到一个目录下面
we can also move it under a directory
从而达到更细的一个管理
as to achieve a better management
我们定一个目录叫front_of_house
We set a directory called front_of_house
那这里面的话有
Then there are three files inside
三个文件
一个是mod.rs 定义了我们所有的
One is that mod.rs, it defines all submodules
front_of_house模块里面所有的子模块
那
Then
相应的我们有一个hosting的子模块
we have a hosting submodule
以及一个serving的子模块
and a serving submodule
我们把对应的代码粘出来
Let's copy and paste the corresponding code
hosting的模块代码是在这里
The hosting module code is here
以及我们
and the code of serving
serving对应代码也粘出来
那我们在front_of_house目录
Then we need to define serving and hosting in mod.rs/front_of_house
的mod.rs
里面我们就需要
Then we need to define serving and hosting in mod.rs/front_of_house
定义我们对应的模块
hosting
Then we need to define serving and hosting in mod.rs/front_of_house
以及我们的serving
可以看到我们这里使用pub关键字
You can see that we use the "pub" keyword here
让我们的模块变得可见
to make our module public visible
这样我们的front_of_house就不再需要了
This way our front_of_house is no longer needed
接着我们来编译执行 我们需要保存
Let's try to compile and execute the code
可以看到现在还是执行成功
We can see that the execution is still successful
这样我们就有了一个
Now we have a clearer code structure
比较清晰的代码结构
那我们现在可以看我们
We also notice that
引入的路径很长
the path to import is long
我们可以使用use
Actually, we can use a keyword to import modules
关键字把我们对应的模块引入进来
我们就直接可以通过
We can call hosting::add_to_waitlist directly
hosting::add_to_waitlist来直接调用
可以看到我们两次调用都是成功的
You can see that our two calls are successful
同样的我们可以使用as来进行别名
Similarly, we can use as to alias
比如我们直接用host
For example, we directly alias the module to host
这样我们hosting改成host
In this way, we change hosting to host
重新调用也是成功的
The call is also successful
我们的代码演示就到这里
That's all for our code demo
接着我们来看一下workspace
then let's take a look at the workspace
workspace的好处是
The benefits of workspace are
它可以管理多个library和binary
it can manage multiple libraries and binaries
并且它共享了Cargo.lock文件
and it shares the Cargo.lock file
以及编译输出目录
and the compiled output directory
这样当我们在编译多个库的时候
So when we are compiling multiple libraries
或者binary的时候
or binary
可以减少编译时间 增加我们的编译效率
it increase our compilation efficiency
另外一个好处是
Another benefit is
不同的library和binary之间
Among different libraries and binary
他们的依赖是彼此隔离的
their dependencies are isolated from each other
也就是说
That is to say
你在一个workspace的
in a workspace
A library里面引入的一个库
modules imported in the A library
在B library并不能直接使用
they cannot be used directly in the B library
还需要在B library的
we need to import modules again B library's Cargo.toml
Cargo.toml里面进行引入
才可以用
we need to import modules again B library's Cargo.toml
那这里我们列出了cargo workspace
Here we havea reference of the Cargo-workspace
一个参考资料
大家感兴趣的话可以看一下
if you are interested, you can take a look
我们现在来看一个demo
Let's take a look at a demo now
那这个demo的话其实就是Substrate
Then this demo is actually Substrate source code
源代码
可以看到它有非常多的文件目录
You can see that it has a lot of file directories
它有一个Cargo.toml
It has a cargo.toml
我们打开看一下
let's open it
它定义了一个workspace
It defines a workspace
所以我们的Substrate源代码
the Substrate source code, in fact, it is a typical workspace
其实是一个典型的workspace
组织的一个应用
like an organization, there are many members
它有非常多的成员
那不同的成员
The different members are defined in different directories
定义在不同的目录里面
比如说
For example
bin里面定义了可执行的一些binary
sSome executable binaries are defined in the bin
比如node
such as node
它是一个功能非常完善的节点程序
it is a very full-featured node program
node template大家应该比较熟悉了
You should be familiar with node template
它是一个最小化的节点代码程序
it is a minimal node code program
utils里面包含了一些工具组件
The utils contains some tool components
比如subkey
such as subkey for key management
用来进行密钥管理
那client目录里面包含了
The client directory contains
节点客户端所需要必备的一些功能
some functions required by the node client
比如网络传输层, 交易池
such as network transport layer, transaction pool, consensus
共识相关的等等
and database operations
以及数据库的读写操作
那frame里面包含的是我们
The frame contains
编写runtime
some basic functional components required when we write runtimes
所需要的一些基础功能组件
以及我们常用的一些runtime的模块
and some of our commonly used runtime modules
比如资产
such as assets
primitive里面定义了
The primitive contains
Substrate里面核心的一些
core data structures and functions in the Substrate
数据结构和功能
感兴趣大家
If you are interested
可以仔细去读一下源码
you can read the source code
我们今天的作业内容是第一题
This is the assignment for this lesson
为我们的枚举
The first is to mplement a trait for the enum of traffic light
数据类型交通信号灯实现一个trait
那这个trait里面包含
This trait should contain
了一个返回时间的方法
a function that returns a time
不同的信号灯应该返回的时间不同
The duration of each light shoule be different
第二道题是实现一个函数
The second one is to implement a function
它能够为u32类型的整数集合进行求和
that can sum a collection of integers of type u32
参数类型是一个slice
the parameter type is a slice
返回类型为一个Option
The return type is an Option
当求和溢出时返回None
returns None when the sum overflows
第三道题是
The third question is
实现一个打印图形面积的函数
Implement a function to print the area of ​​graphics
他接收一个可以计算面积的
It takes a type that its area can be calculated as a parameter
类型作为参数
这个类型可以是圆形, 三角形, 正方形
This type can be circle, triangle, square
那我们这里就需要用到泛型来表示
Then we need to use generic types to represent such a variety type
这样的一个多种
类型的可能性
Then we need to use generic types to represent such a variety type
以及泛型约束来保证我们这个
and generic constraints to ensure that
类型是可以计算面积的
the type's area can be calculated
今天课程的内容就到这里
That's all for today's lesson
谢谢大家
thank you all